Maass, Joachim; Papers ger063
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Joachim Maass Papers
1901-1972
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
ger063
2.5 cubic ft.
The collection contains correspondence, manuscript materials and lecture notes.
Biographical History
A writer, Joachim Maass (1901-1972) was born in Hamburg and came to the United States in 1938. He secured a positon at Mount Holyoke College in 1940, where he taught and lectured. He later taught German literature at Haverford College.
Scope and Contents
The collection is composed entirely of photocopied materials. The originals are in the Deutsches Literaturarchiv, Marbach, Germany. The collection includes correspondence, manuscripts of novels, short stories, plays, poetry, and essays, 1940-46; lecture notes, 1956-61; and clippings, offprints, reviews, and biographies, 1927-36.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is divided into eight series.
Acquisition Information
The M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives received the papers from University at Albany Professor John Spalek in January 1977. Professor Spalek received them from retired Haverford College and West Chester(Pennsylvania) State College Professor Harry Pfund and his wife Marie Pfund in January 1977. The M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives photocopied the papers before the originals were sent to the Deutsches Literaturarchiv, Marbach in 1977. This was per Professor Pfund's request.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Literature; World War, 1939-1945 -- Refugees; Short stories; Correspondence; Poems; Essays; Maass, Joachim, 1901-1972
- Correspondence, contracts, 1930-1972; 1
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  Contains two folders of correspondence.
  - Correspondence with the Kurt Desch Vrlag, concerning Maass' works. Also contracts, 1961; 1969; 1971-1972; Undated (Box 1 (1-Correspondence, contracts), Folder 1)
  - Stefan Zweig, 1930-1939 (Box 1 (1-Correspondence, contracts), Folder 2)
- Manuscripts - Novels, Undated; 2
  Arranged in original order.
  This series contains manuscript novels and fragments of novels.
  - Carl Schurz, Undated (Box 1 (2-Manuscripts - Novels), Folder 3)
  - Senator, Innenministier und "Mugwump" Fuehrer [Carl Schurz], Undated (Box 1 (2-Manuscripts - Novels), Folder 4)
  - Schurz, Undated (Box 1 (2-Manuscripts - Novels), Folder 5)
  - Schurz in Deutschland, Undated (Box 1 (2-Manuscripts - Novels), Folder 6)
  - The Lawmaker. Adventures ... and bequest of Carl Schurz, Undated (Box 1 (2-Manuscripts - Novels), Folder 7)
  - "Deutsche Schule 1918. Ein Romankapitel." p. 1-7, 21-26, 34-39. Gouff +Roman de la Ronciere, Undated (Box 1 (2-Manuscripts - Novels), Folder 8)
  - Zur Geschichtedes Romans. Der Fall Gouffe, Undated (Box 1 (2-Manuscripts - Novels), Folder 9)
  - Roman de la Ronciere, Undated (Box 1 (2-Manuscripts - Novels), Folder 10)
  - Roman de la Ronciere. "Roman - 2. Band", Undated (Box 1 (2-Manuscripts - Novels), Folder 11)
  - La Ronciere und Marie Morell, Undated (Box 1 (2-Manuscripts - Novels), Folder 12)
  - La Ronciere und Marie Morell. Plot summary, characters, notes, Undated (Box 1 (2-Manuscripts - Novels), Folder 13)
  - Thomas und Maria. Erste Fassung, Undated (Box 1 (2-Manuscripts - Novels), Folder 14)
  - The Times Collapse, Undated (Box 1 (2-Manuscripts - Novels), Folder 15)
  - True Story?, Undated (Box 1 (2-Manuscripts - Novels), Folder 16)
  - Zwischen den Zeizen / Astride the Times, Undated (Box 1 (2-Manuscripts - Novels), Folder 17)
  - "Notizen zu Band II 'Zwischen den Zeiten.' Neue Fassung", Undated (Box 1 (2-Manuscripts - Novels), Folder 18)
  - Untitled Manuscript in English, Undated (Box 1 (2-Manuscripts - Novels), Folder 19)
- Manuscripts - Dramatic works, Undated; 3
  This series contains manuscripts of dramatic works.
  - "The Case of Lieutenant de la Ronciere. A Television Play by Joachim Maass." Translated by Holger Hagen, Undated (Box 1 (3-Manuscripts - Dramatic works), Folder 20)
  - Heinrich der Vierte. Tragdie in 2 Teilen (22 Bilder), Undated (Box 1 (3-Manuscripts - Dramatic works), Folder 21)
  - "Kain. Dramatische Skizze von W. H. J. Maass", Undated (Box 1 (3-Manuscripts - Dramatic works), Folder 22)
  - Die Zwillingsbrdder (Arbeitstitel). Kombdie in vier Akten, Undated (Box 1 (3-Manuscripts - Dramatic works), Folder 23)
- Manuscripts - Poetry, Undated; 4
  This series contains manuscripts of poems.
  - "Die enge Pforte." Collection of poems, Undated (Box 1 (4-Manuscripts - Poetry), Folder 24)
  - "Frdhe handschriftliche Gedichte", Undated (Box 1 (4-Manuscripts - Poetry), Folder 25)
  - "GesAnge vom guten Geschick", Undated (Box 1 (4-Manuscripts - Poetry), Folder 26)
  - "Handgeschriebene Gedichle", Undated (Box 1 (4-Manuscripts - Poetry), Folder 27)
  - "Kleine handschriftliche Arbeiten handschriftliche Gedichte", Undated (Box 1 (4-Manuscripts - Poetry), Folder 28)
  - "Neue Gedichte", Undated (Box 1 (4-Manuscripts - Poetry), Folder 29)
  - "Vers und Prosa", Undated (Box 1 (4-Manuscripts - Poetry), Folder 30)
  - "Vom lusitanischen Parnass. Nachdichtungen jngerer portugiesischer Lyrik", Undated (Box 1 (4-Manuscripts - Poetry), Folder 31)
  - "Gedichte, Herbst 1927", Undated (Box 1 (4-Manuscripts - Poetry), Folder 32)
  - Poems, Undated (Box 1 (4-Manuscripts - Poetry), Folder 33)
- Manuscripts - Short prose works, stories, 1946, Undated; 5
  This series contains manuscripts of short prose and stories.
  - "Die Alsterfahrt", Undated (Box 2 (5-Manuscripts - Short prose works, stories), Folder 1)
  - "Anjuta odor Die Schule der Armut. I. Teil eines Erzhlungsbuch 'Junge Leute'", Undated (Box 2 (5-Manuscripts - Short prose works, stories), Folder 2)
  - "Das begnadete Herz", Undated (Box 2 (5-Manuscripts - Short prose works, stories), Folder 3)
  - "Ein Leben nach dem Tode", Undated (Box 2 (5-Manuscripts - Short prose works, stories), Folder 4)
  - "Ein Schulmorgen", Undated (Box 2 (5-Manuscripts - Short prose works, stories), Folder 5)
  - "Das Erwachen", Undated (Box 2 (5-Manuscripts - Short prose works, stories), Folder 6)
  - "Das Frauenbchlein. Briefe und Gedichte in Prosa", Undated (Box 2 (5-Manuscripts - Short prose works, stories), Folder 7)
  - "Die Hand des Herrn, oder: Der bse Blick", 1946 October 14; Undated (Box 2 (5-Manuscripts - Short prose works, stories), Folder 8)
  - "Der bse Blick. Eine Erzhlung", Undated (Box 2 (5-Manuscripts - Short prose works, stories), Folder 9)
  - "Die Liebe der Boheme. Eine Erzhlung", Undated (Box 2 (5-Manuscripts - Short prose works, stories), Folder 10)
  - "Man macht sich falsche Vorstellungen von der Emigration", Undated (Box 2 (5-Manuscripts - Short prose works, stories), Folder 11)
  - "Missdeurcete Liebe", Undated (Box 2 (5-Manuscripts - Short prose works, stories), Folder 12)
  - "Nordlandsflug", Undated (Box 2 (5-Manuscripts - Short prose works, stories), Folder 13)
  - "Der Schnee von Nebraska. Eileitung", Undated (Box 2 (5-Manuscripts - Short prose works, stories), Folder 14)
  - "The Snow of Nebraska." English Translation, Undated (Box 2 (5-Manuscripts - Short prose works, stories), Folder 15)
  - "Sonntagliches Holland", Undated (Box 2 (5-Manuscripts - Short prose works, stories), Folder 16)
  - "Das Werk des Bildhauers Harry Rox", Undated (Box 2 (5-Manuscripts - Short prose works, stories), Folder 17)
  - "Zware Nevel." Dutch translation, Undated (Box 2 (5-Manuscripts - Short prose works, stories), Folder 18)
  - Miscellaneous short manuscripts, Undated (Box 2 (5-Manuscripts - Short prose works, stories), Folder 19)
- Manuscripts - Essayistic, 1940-1946; 6
  This series contains manuscripts of essays.
  - Autobiographical sketch, Undated; T. 5p. Digital Files (Box 2 (6-Manuscripts - Essayistic), Folder 20)
  - "Als Greenhorn in Amerika. Eine Vorlesung", Undated; T. 15p. Digital Files (Box 2 (6-Manuscripts - Essayistic), Folder 21)
  - "Daran glaube ich", Undated; T. 3p. Digital Files (Box 2 (6-Manuscripts - Essayistic), Folder 22)
  - "Ein Abschiedsbrief", Undated; T. with h. corr. 13p. T. with h. corr. llp. Digital Files (Box 2 (6-Manuscripts - Essayistic), Folder 23)
  - "Friedo Lampe", Undated; T. with h. corr. 6p. Digital Files (Box 2 (6-Manuscripts - Essayistic), Folder 24)
  - "Imaginierter Toast zu Carl Zuckmayers 50. Geburtstag", 1946 December 27; T. and cc. 2c. 8p. ea. Digital Files (Box 2 (6-Manuscripts - Essayistic), Folder 25)
  - "Leben, Sterben und Unsrerblichkeit Rainer Maria Rilkes. Ein Vor-trag" plus several p. Rilke poems., 1940 November 25; 1941 March 26; 1942 March 25; T. 25p. Digital Files (Box 2 (6-Manuscripts - Essayistic), Folder 26)
  - Meetings with Thomas Mann", Undated (Box 2 (6-Manuscripts - Essayistic), Folder 27)
  - "Der sechzigjhrige Martin Beheim-Schwarzbach", Undated; T. cc. 5p. Digital Files (Box 2 (6-Manuscripts - Essayistic), Folder 28)
  - "Schurz, Lincoln und die Seele Amerikas. Eine Vorlesung", Undated; T. with h. corr. 29p. Digital Files (Box 2 (6-Manuscripts - Essayistic), Folder 29)
  - Thomas Mann. Geschichte einer Liebe im Geiste", Undated; T. cc. 28p. Digital Files (Box 2 (6-Manuscripts - Essayistic), Folder 30)
  - "Thomas Mann. An Essay. English translation, Undated; T. with h. corr. 28p. Digital Files (Box 2 (6-Manuscripts - Essayistic), Folder 31)
  - "Ueber die Kriterien der Dichtung. Eine Einleitung zu einem, College-Text", Undated; T. 41p. Digital Files (Box 2 (6-Manuscripts - Essayistic), Folder 32)
  - "Unser kleinen Dmon." Notes, Undated; ca. 40p. Digital Files (Box 2 (6-Manuscripts - Essayistic), Folder 33)
  - "Vorwort" and "Schlusswort" to an unidentified work, Undated; T.cc. l2p., 4p. Digital Files (Box 2 (6-Manuscripts - Essayistic), Folder 34)
  - "Wir Hamburger", Undated; T. with some h. corr. 12p. Digital Files (Box 2 (6-Manuscripts - Essayistic), Folder 35)
- Lecture notes, texts, 1957-1961; 7
  Arranged chronologically by lecture.
  This collection contains lecture notes from Haverford College. Each lecture has multiple dates, presumably relating to the dates Joachim Maass gave the lecture during different academic semesters.
  - Haverford Lectures, First and Second Lectures, 1959; 1961 (Box 2 (7-Lecture notes, texts), Folder 36)
  - Haverford Lectures, Third Lecture, 1961 (Box 2 (7-Lecture notes, texts), Folder 37)
  - Haverford Lectures, Postponed Third Lecture, 1957 (Box 2 (7-Lecture notes, texts), Folder 38)
  - Haverford Lectures, Fourth Lecture, 1959 (Box 2 (7-Lecture notes, texts), Folder 39)
  - Haverford Lectures, Fifth Lecture, 1961 (Box 2 (7-Lecture notes, texts), Folder 40)
  - Haverford Lectures, Sixth Lecture, 1959; 1961 (Box 2 (7-Lecture notes, texts), Folder 41)
  - Haverford Lectures, Seventh Lecture, 1957; 1959; 1961 (Box 2 (7-Lecture notes, texts), Folder 42)
  - Haverford Lectures, Eighth Lecture, 1959; 1961 (Box 2 (7-Lecture notes, texts), Folder 43)
  - Haverford Lectures, Ninth Lecture, 1957; 1959; 1961 (Box 2 (7-Lecture notes, texts), Folder 44)
  - Haverford Lectures, Tenth Lecture, 1957; 1959; 1961 (Box 2 (7-Lecture notes, texts), Folder 45)
  - Haverford Lectures, Eleventh Lecture, 1957; 1959; 1961 (Box 2 (7-Lecture notes, texts), Folder 46)
  - Haverford Lectures, Twelfth Lecture, 1957-1959; 1961 (Box 2 (7-Lecture notes, texts), Folder 47)
  - Haverford Lectures, Thirteenth Lecture, 1957; 1959; 1961 (Box 2 (7-Lecture notes, texts), Folder 48)
  - Lecture Notes, 1957 (Box 2 (7-Lecture notes, texts), Folder 49)
  - Lecture Notebooks, 1957 (Box 2 (7-Lecture notes, texts), Folder 50)
- Published materials, biographical materials, 1901-1969; 8
  This series contains biographical materials such as a birth certificate and award as well as clippings about Joachim Maass and his published works.
  - Biographical clippings, 1932; 1945; 1960-1961; 1964; Undated (Box 2 (8-Published materials, biographical materials), Folder 51)
  - "Beitrge fr die Vossische Zeitung"-I. clippings, 1927-1929 (Box 2 (8-Published materials, biographical materials), Folder 52)
  - "Beitrge fr die Vossische Zeitung"-clippings, 1945-1946; Undated (Box 2 (8-Published materials, biographical materials), Folder 53)
  - Clippings, published works, 1927; 1930; 1932-1933; 1949 (Box 2 (8-Published materials, biographical materials), Folder 54)
  - Documents, 1901-1963 (Box 2 (8-Published materials, biographical materials), Folder 55)
  - Leben, Sterben und Unsterlichkeit Rainer Maria Rikes, 1940-1942 (Box 3 (8-Published materials, biographical materials), Folder 1)
  - Imaginierter Toast zu Carl Zuckmayers, 1946 (Box 3 (8-Published materials, biographical materials), Folder 2)
  - "Beitrge fr die Vossische Zeitung", 1927-1932 (Box 3 (8-Published materials, biographical materials), Folder 3)
  - "Beitrge frs Hamburger Freundesblatt" I, 1927 October 29-1929 August 24 (Box 3 (8-Published materials, biographical materials), Folder 4)
  - "Beitrge frs Hamburger Freundesblatt" II, 1929 August-1932 August (Box 3 (8-Published materials, biographical materials), Folder 5)
  - "Beitrge frs Hamburger Freundesblatt" III, 1932 August-1936 December (Box 3 (8-Published materials, biographical materials), Folder 6)
  - Vorlesungen im Kurs, Problems of Red-education in Post-War Germany, 1969; Undated (Box 3 (8-Published materials, biographical materials), Folder 7)
  - Hesse/Th. Mann., 1935-1941; 1944-1949; 1951-1952; 1956; 1958-1960 (Box 3 (8-Published materials, biographical materials), Folder 8)